Okay. So, what I'm going to show you in
this video is how to use the and
operator and the or operator and also
some considerations that you need to
make when you're using those operators.
So, um I've built here um an input that
will get their username and the user's
password. And then I have some variables
that I've coded in that are just storing
a username and a password in an email.
Um and I realized I actually probably
need to get their email, too. Uh we'll
do that in a minute, though. So let's
get started. So let's say I want to see
if their username and password are
correct. So I could say if username is
exactly the same as the input username,
then I would alert
correct.
But I also want to check a second
condition. I want to see if their
username
and their password was correct. So if I
want to check two conditions at a time,
then I need to use another operator. So
I want to say if the username is exactly
equal to the input username, then I'm
going to use the amperand twice. The
amperand is above the seven key on your
keyboard. So if you hold shift and 7,
it'll give you the amperand.
So I want to see if their username is
exactly the same as their input
username. and I want to see if their
password is exactly the same as the
password they input. If they did, I'm
going to tell them
welcome to the system.
Otherwise, I'm going to say alert
wrong
username or password.
So, I'm going to save this and let's go
see it live. Says, what is your
username? And I think to was what I
used. What is your password? Password.
And it said welcome to the system. If we
reload, it says what is your username
and what is your password? We give the
wrong password. Says wrong username or
password. Um so that's how you can check
two conditions. So that's if you want
both conditions to be true. So if you
want the first condition to be true and
the second condition to be true in order
to do whatever you're doing next, you'll
use the amperand.
Sometimes you don't care which one is
correct as long as one of them is
correct. So, let's adjust this. Um,
let's say we're entering a system that
doesn't have a password. I don't know
why that would be, but let's say that's
happening. Um, let's say we're just
checking if they either know their
username or their email. So, we'll say
if username Oh, this is now where we'll
need to gather that information. So, I'm
going to hold option shift and hit the
down arrow. And that will copy the above
line down to the line I was just on. If
you're on a Windows, it's alt and then
shift and then the down arrow. So option
shift down arrow or alt shift down arrow
will copy a line of code for you. I'm
going to change this from input password
to input username
and I'm going to oh sorry input input
email. And I'm going to change the word
password to email. So, I'm now asking
them for their username, their password,
and their email. I don't like email on
this line. I want to ask for it right
after username. So, I'm going to hold
the option and hit the up arrow. And
that moves the line of code I was on up
a line. If you're on a Windows, you will
hold the Alt key and hit the up arrow.
And that moves the line of code around
based on where your cursor is at. So,
I'm gathering in their username, their
email, and their password. And then I'm
checking it against the username,
password, and email. In this case, if
their username is the same as the
username or if they've entered the
correct email address. So, if their
input email is exactly the same as the
email, then I want to say welcome to the
system. Otherwise, I want to say wrong
username or password. So, I'm going to
come in and it's going to say, what is
your username? And I'm going to enter
the wrong one here and what is your
email? And I'm going to enter the right
one here.
And then it's going to say what is my
password? And I'm going to enter
gibberish. And it says welcome to the
system. So notice I entered the wrong
username but the right email. And
because of this or operator because one
of the conditions was met, it allowed me
into the system.
One of the considerations you have to
take into account is something called a
dangling ore. So I'm going to
demonstrate this for you. So, I'm going
to say if the username is this or the
email is this.
Um, and then so I want it to be if they
enter either the correct username or the
correct email. And then I also want to
make sure they entered the right
password. So I'll say if they've got
either the right username and the right
email and they have the right password.
Um,
input password. then I want to welcome
to the system otherwise I want to say
wrong username or password now you would
think that this would work let's go try
it so what is your username uh my
username was to what is my email to
pizza schooledu
what is your password
and it let us in try that again what is
your username
toa what is your p email something wrong
which should totally work. What is your
password? Let's put something wrong
there, too. It still let us in. So,
because we've put that or on there,
the way this works is the or will get
rearranged to the end. So, it means it's
going to check to see if the password's
correct or
if they got the username right or the
email. Any one of those, they'll let you
in the system. Now, that's not what we
wanted. So what we want to do is we want
to use parenthesis. Parenthesis force a
condition to be checked in a certain
order. So what we're going to say is
we're going to say if the username
is the right username or the email is
the right email,
then after we've checked that they have
one of those two things, then we'll see
if at least one of those was correct and
the password is correct, then we'll
welcome them to the system. So, we'll
save and we'll reload our page and it'll
say what is your username and I'll say
to what is your email? I'll put
gibberish. What is your password? I'll
put gibberish. It says wrong username or
password. We reload the page. What is
your username? Toa. What is your email?
Gibberish. What is your password?
Password. And it says welcome to the
system. So now what it's doing because
of the parenthesis, it's first checking
to see if we've got the right username
or the right password. It doesn't
matter. I say right username or right
email. Doesn't matter which one as long
as we have one of them. Once it's
figured that out, it checks if we have
one of those and the correct password.
If we don't have the correct password or
we don't have the correct um one of the
username or the email, then it won't let
us in. But if we have both a correct
username or email and the correct
password, then it'll let us in. Maybe
you're like me and this is giving you a
bit of a headache. Um well, I'm going to
show you the other way to do this. I
generally like to avoid writing ands and
ors where possible because um it leaves
room for me to make a mistake and leave
a dangling ore on the end that um does
something unexpected. So I'm going to
rewrite this um using nested if
statements. So what I'm going to say is
I'm going to say if the username
um
is exactly the same as the input
username
or and we will use the or here the input
email is exactly the same as the email.
Then I want to see if the password
is exactly the same as the input
password.
If it is, then I'm going to alert.
Welcome to the system.
If
the username is not the same as the
input username and the email is or the
email is not the same, meaning if they
got neither of those right, then I'll
say else alert,
wrong username.
And then
here we'll say else alert
wrong
username or password.
So they'll come in, they can enter
either the username or the email. If
they get the right one, then it'll ask
them for a password and it'll say
welcome to the system. Otherwise, it'll
alert wrong username or password. And
then down here, that's probably not the
right thing to put here. we'd probably
want to put, "Sorry, can't find an
account with that username." So now they
can either enter the username or the
email as long as one of those is
correct, then it'll ask them for a
password. If neither of those is
correct, then it'll tell them, "Sorry,
no account with that username."
If it is, if one of those is correct,
then it'll check the password. So, it's
doing the same thing as the if statement
on the line above, but you don't have to
worry about the dangling or, and you
don't have to worry about complicated
parenthesis. So, where possible, you'll
probably want to avoid those, but
occasionally you'll find a situation
where it's unavoidable. Make sure you're
using parenthesis in the right location.
And that should conclude this video on
and and or. Thank you for watching.